<changelog xmlns:r="http://www.r-project.org"
	   xmlns:omg="http://www.omegahat.org"
           xmlns:env="http://www.shell.org">
<omg:pkg>RJSONIO</omg:pkg>

<version num="0.98-0">
<change>
Update default libjson code to version 7.4.0.
</change>
<change>
Changes to configuration to allow the use of a version
of libjson that is not installed but not in the RJSONIO
package directory itself. Use the environment variable
<env:var>LIBJSON_SRC</env:var>.
</change>
<change>
Configuration determines version of libjson and adapts compilation flags accordingly.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.97-0">
<change>
Add <r:func>isValidJSON</r:func> to test whether the JSON content is
valid.  Suggested by Jeroen Ooms.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.96-0">
<change>
Added encoding argument for <r:func>fromJSON</r:func> and that encoding is preserved on
the resulting strings. Thanks to Tony Breyal for pointing out the issue.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.95-0">
<change>
In <r:func>fromJSON</r:func>, when <r:arg>nullValue</r:arg> is <r:na/> (the logical NA)
we attempt to simplify vectors with JSON null values.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.94-0">
<change>
Added <r:arg>simplifyWithNames</r:arg> to <r:func>fromJSON</r:func> for controlling whether we attempt to collapse
collections of values read from JSON if they have names.  This can be used to collapse unnamed
vectors, but leave named lists that would otherwise be collapsed to vectors.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.93-0">
<change>
Added support in fromJSON<r:func></r:func> for collapsing particular types of elements,
i.e. logicals, numbers or characters via 
 <r:var>StrictLogical</r:var>, <r:var>StrictNumeric</r:var> and <r:var>StrictCharacter</r:var>.
This allows "strict" collapsing, but for different types, while leaving others as lists.
These can be combined.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.92-0">
<change>
Added to the ability to control whether we simplify the content using simplify = Strict or <r:true/> or <r:false/>.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.91-0">
<change>
Added <r:arg>.escapeEscapes</r:arg> to <r:func>toJSON</r:func> to allow the caller
to preserve new lines and tabs symbolically or not. Thanks to Antonio Piccolboni for the report about the issue.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.9-0">
<change>
Added <r:arg>.na</r:arg> parameter to the <r:func>toJSON</r:func> function and methods
so that the caller can control how <r:na/> values are mapped to JSON.
This defaults to "null" so that the resulting JSON is well-formed.
However, users should explicitly think  about how <r:na/> values 
(and Inf and NaN) are mapped to JSON in order to avoid ambiguity and
faithfully serialize their data in a meaningful manner.
</change>
<change>
Added a <r:arg>nullValue</r:arg> parameter to <r:func>fromJSON</r:func>
to allow the caller to provide an R object that will be used
when we encounter a JSON null value. 
This can be used for example to map null to <r:na/> in R.
</change>
<change>
Added more support for simplifying lists to vectors of different types. 
In the future, I might add a simplify = "strict" mode that would
only collapse vectors if all the elements were of the same type,
not just compatible types. In other words,
 [true, 1 ] would not collapse to c(1, 1) in R.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.8-2">
<change>
Corrected what toJSON() does with new lines (\n) and avoid the escaping of the \. Thanks to 
Antonio Piccolboni for the report.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.8-1">
<change>
Corrections to the libjson C/C++ code from Brian Ripley.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.8-0">
<change>
Added a <r:arg>.withNames</r:arg> parameter to <r:func>toJSON</r:func>
so that the caller can explicitly control whether an R object with names
is written as an associative array or as a simple array.
</change>

<change>
Added a <r:arg>simplify</r:arg> parameter to <r:func>fromJSON</r:func> 
that controls whether we collapse lists of homogeneous element types
to an R vector.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.7-3">
<change>
Added .withNames parameter for <r:func>toJSON</r:func> which allows the
caller to control whether we ignore or use any names. Defaults to 
use the names if they are present.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.7-3">
<change>
Honor the collapse argument in more places to allow avoiding new line characters being
inserted.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.7-2">
<change>
Copied compiler flags for libjson code into Makevars.win
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.7-1">
<change>
Correction for toJSON() method for handling of \ in strings so that they round-trip and work in other JSON tools.
     Thanks to Patrick Perry.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.7-0">
<change>
Round-tripping from JSON to R and back behaves a lot more consistently.
Thanks to Kevin Coombes for the examples/tests.<br/>
Next, we will add functionality to customize serialization of <r:na/>.
</change>
<change>
Change to the default value of <r:arg>container</r:arg> of <r:func>toJSON</r:func> so that 
this is  <r:true/> when at the top-level or initial call to <r:func>toJSON</r:func>.
</change>
<change>
We now know the type of the top-most node so can correctly handle empty 
associative arrays, etc.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.6-0">
<change>
 Updated the libjson source code in the package to libjson 7.0.1.
     This removes a bug in parsing numbers of the form 3.14E4. Found
     by Jeroen Ooms.
</change>
<change>
Added configuration so that we can use a libjson installed on the system.
   This avoids issues of using older versions of libjson shipped with this package.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.5-0">
<change>Enhancements to disambiguate serializing empty lists from as empty arrays or associative 
arrays.  See also emptyNamedList to map to {}. 
</change>
<change>Method for identifying an R scalar that should be mapped to a JSON array via the 
AsIs class and I() function.
</change>
<change>toJSON() honors these also ensuring transformation from JSON to R to JSON
preserves the same structure.
</change>
<change>
     Both changes thanks to suggestions by Keith Bonawitz.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.4-2">
<change>Fixed significant memory leaks found by Keith Bonawitz</change>
</version>

<version num="0.4-1">
<change>Tidied up C++ code from libjsonio to avoid a warning about no
     argument to initializeFetch() when compiling the C++ code.
</change>
<change>Fixed a C routine (R_fromJSON) that did not return a value.</change>
</version>

<version num="0.4-0">
<change>
<r:func>fromJSON</r:func> now uses libjson for the native parsing
and a C routine to transform the resulting tree into R.
This leads to a considerable speedup in parsing documents,
approximately a factor of 200 over the customizable, event
driven mechanism in earlier versions and still available 
in this package via the <r:func>basicJSONHandler</r:func>
function and <r:func>fromJSON</r:func>.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.3-4">
<change>Refinement of handling large integers that do not fit into a 4 byte int.
Tested on Windows.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.3-3">
<change>Handle large integers that do not fit into a 4 byte int. Return as numeric values.</change>
</version>

<version num="0.3-1">
<change>Convert factors to character vectors in <r:func>toJSON</r:func> and then serialize.</change>
</version>

<version num="0.2-4">
<change>Handles UTF-8 content  as input. We convert the text to raw and then integer
values.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.2-3">
<change>(Minor) Change to the C code to make it compile on Windows.</change>
</version>

<version num="0.2-2">
<change>
named atomic/primitive vectors serialized as associative arrays rather
than simple arrays.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.2-1">
<change>
names on R objects from associative arrays from JSON were in reverse order.
</change>
</version>

<version num="0.2-0">
<change>
Scalar, by default, values are represented in JSON as scalars and not
arrays of length 1.  One can control this via the
<r:arg>container</r:arg> parameter in <r:func>toJSON</r:func>.
</change>
</version>

</changelog>
